A Guide to the Lyman Creighton Craig papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA134
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Laboratory data, 8
  - Insulin, 1953 1954 1955 1956 1957 1959 1960 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    Correspondence with Armour Co. and Lilly Research Labs. Includes various copies of experimental data on Lily insulin and measurements of various preparations of Armour and Lilly insulin; also photographs of figure and formula for #165 in Craig bibliography. pp 1-103.
  - Luciferin, 1961, undated (Box 41, Folder 5)
    Literature; lab notes; summary. pp 1-4.
  - Substance "P", 3 folders (Box 41)
    - Substance "P", 1961-1968 (Box 41, Folder 6)
      (Collaborators: Vogler (Hoffmann-LaRoche) and Zuber (Ciba, Basle).
      Correspondence; (some photocopied) includes reports; literature; review of Shaw and Ramwell ms. for publication in American J. Physiology. pp 0-143.
    - Substance "P" (Box 41, Folder 7)
      Amino acid analyses. pp 1-109.
    - Substance "P", 1965 (Box 41, Folder 8)
      Forman ms. 1965 Summer biochemistry course research project. David Forman (RU graduate student) ms. "A study of a substance from brain tissue which stimulates smooth muscle". pp 1-20.
      [Under direction of H. Meinardi in Craig lab].
  - Parathyroid hormone (Box 42, Folder 1)
    Includes 2 items correspondence; amino acid analyses for Rasmussen and Craig "Isolation and characterization of bovine parathyroid hormone" [So indicated on original folder] #169 in bibliography with reprint.
    Also includes copy of Rasmussen et al ms "Further studies on the isolation and characterization of parathyroid polypeptides" with figures. pp 0-34.
  - Peptides, 1969 February 1 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    S. Moore and W.J. (?) photocopies of note for file "Experiment on the color yields of L-isoleucyl-L-isoleucine and L-Valyl-l-valine". pp 1-3.
  - Polymyxin, 1963-1972 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    [See also under Hoffmann-LaRoche in box no. 6].
    Includes correspondence with K. Vogler and O. Isler; reports; literature; lab notes with measurements.
    Collaborative work with Hoffmann-LaRoche on polymyxin. pp 0-89.
  - Protamines, 1950 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    3 items correspondence only on obtaining samples. pp 1-3.
  - Secretin, 1970 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    Dr. Craig performs diffusion studies on secretin for Squibb.
    Correspondence includes report on diffusion studies on; also includes lab data. pp 0-12.
  - Subtilin, 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Subtilin studies, 1955-1959 (Box 42, Folder 6)
      Correspondence includes annotated bibliography of subtilin and literature; also includes partial ms. "The structure of subtilin".
      [See #158 in Craig bibliography - different title] with figures for #158; lab measurements and data. pp 0-69.
    - Subtilin, 1957-1958 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      Amino acid analyses. pp 1-73.
  - Tyrocidine, 1964-1970 (Box 42, Folder 8)
    Correspondence includes mss by others. Also includes laboratory data. pp 0-85.
  - Tyrocidine-C spectrophat. Titration, 1962 December 3 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    Includes lab notes and measurements. pp 1-9.
  - Tyrocidine temperature studies, 1962 1964 (Box 42, Folder 10)
    Measurements. pp 1-13.
  - Tyrocidine model photographs (M. Ruttenberg), circa 1966 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    Includes photocopy of M.A. Ruttenberg 1966 ms. pp 0-40.
  - Ultracentrifuge (David A. Yphantis), 1959-1960 (Box 42, Folder 12)
    Includes copy of advance notes for Yphantis 1960 Jan. 27 RU seminar on "Analytical ultra-centrifugation" and photocopy of Yphantis.
    Boston ACS meeting presentation "Ultracentrifugal molecular weight averages during the approach to equilibrium". pp 1-27.
- Laboratory notes, 1947-1970, undated; 9
  Includes correspondence; notes; measurements.
  Arranged in approximate chronological order. Hand numbered consecutively as found. Some not dated. Some notes by investigators in Craig lab.
  - Amino acids, distribution points, 1947 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    Measurements. pp 1-28.
  - Amino acids separations; polymyxin; insulin, 1947 1948 1949 1950 1953 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    Correspondence includes 1948 Dec. 23 R.J. Dubos to L.C. Craig. Short summary of Dubos' in vitro and in vivo tests with Craig samples of Soviet gramicidin and related substances.
    Also includes lab notes; measurements of amino acid separations and other experiments. pp 1-149.
  - Investigations of carrier effect with pyridine systems, 1955 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    Measurements. pp 1-73.
  - Chromatogram measurements, 1956-1957 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    Primarily dialysis of various substances. pp 1-94.
  - Dialysis of ribonuclease and others, 1956-1957; pp 1-124 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Human serum albumin (W. Hausmann) experimental, 1956-1957; 2 folders (Box 43)
    - untitled, pp 1-137 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - untitled, pp 138-281 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Bacitracin sample testing for Commercial Solvent, 1947 1948 1949 1950 1951 1952 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence; lab notes; measurements; literature. pp 1-143.
  - Measurements of bacitracin, insulin, rag weed pollen, 1952 1953 1954 1955; pp 1-84 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Bacitracin. Phenol distribution of bacitracin partial, 1953-1954 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    Primarily measurements; some lab notes. pp 1-87.
  - Bacitracin; dialysis of ribonuclease, 1953 1956 1957 1958 1960 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    Measurements of bacitracin experiments and dialysis of ribonuclease. pp 1-106.
  - Bacitracin (W. Konigsberg), 1957-1958, undated (Box 44)
    Includes: copies of Konigsberg Bacitracin B paper; Konigsberg (undated) NSF research report; Konigsberg (undated) research reports #1-18 (lacking #3); Vienna (?) W. Konigsberg presentation "Bacitracin polypeptides" with Konigsberg and Craig abstract and amino acid analyses of insulin and bacitracin. Also includes 1957 July-1958 July Konigsberg research report In 2 folders:.
    - untitled, pp 1-179 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - untitled, pp 180-383 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - (?) (Win. Stoffel) [1957-1959 W. Stoffel research associate-organic chemistry and assistant physician in hospital], 1958-circa 1960; pp 1-165 (Box 44, Folder 7)
    Studies in the synthesis of structures related to bacitracin A. (Inaugural dissertation).
    Typescript in German and handwritten copy of what appears similar text in English with measurements.
  - Purification of subtilin, 1957 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    Measurements and notes of experiments. pp 1-77.
  - Bacitracin data, 1958 (Box 45, Folder 2)
    Measurements and notes of experiments. pp 0-29.
  - Test of commercial solvents, 1958-1960; pp 1-95 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Measurements of experiments (Box 45, Folder 4)
    Measurements of experiments and hand sketch of continuous dialyzer with identification.
  - Tryptophan, 1960 1961 1963; pp 1-102 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Graphs from membrane testing, 2 folders (Box 45)
    - 1961 February-July, pp 0-58 (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - 1961 November-1962 March, pp 59-171 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Ribonuclease - Rotatory dispersion data, 1962 April-December; pp 0-41 (Box 45, Folder 7)
    Measurements; notes and Crestfield, Stein and Moore reprint.
  - ACTH, 1961 1962 1963 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    Measurements; notes and Snyder and Sayers "Biological half-life of endogenous ACTH" 0-76.
  - ACTH, insulin, bacitracin, triglycine, tetracyclyn and subtilin measurements, [undated]; pp 1-16 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Peptide columns - Yale, [undated]; pp 1-11 (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - Bacitracin, 1966 (Box 45, Folder 11)
    Includes notes and measurements of tyrocidine B, tritium, human and bovine growth hormone and Craig and Stewart reprint pp 0-101.
  - Actinomycin, insulin, diffusion studies and nucleotides, 1966-1967; pp 1-76 (Box 45, Folder 12)
    Includes Peter Woodford to L.C. Craig handwritten note with photocopied graphs of experiments with sodium taurocholate- 14C.
    Notes and measurements.
  - Angiotensin, 1967 1968; pp 1-93 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    Graphs of measurements.
    Includes copy of 1967 Apr 21 L.C. Craig letter to A.C. Paladini about rotatory dispersion studies.
  - M. Burachek notes, 2 folders (Box 46)
    - 1967-1968, 1 black notebook # 1 of 120 pages (handwritten numbers) and pp 1-7 in back of notebook (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - 1968, 1 black bound notebook # 2 of 207 pp (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Ferrichrome experiments, 1967 1970-1971; pp 0-18 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    Emery reprint and measurements.
    Includes correspondence with T. Emery about ferrichrome.
  - Amino acid analyses, 1969-1970; pp 1-72 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Measurements of various peptides, 1970; pp 1-12 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    Includes literature.
  - Measurements of thin film dialysis studies with ACTH peptides, 2 folders (Box 46)
    - 1970 August-1970 December, pp 0-96 (Box 46, Folder 7)
    - 1970 November-1971 May, pp 97-239 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Jo Chang notes, 3 folders (Box 47)
    - Log I for L.C. Craig, 1968; pp 1-298 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Log II for L.C. Craig, 1969; pp 1-299 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Log III for L.C. Craig, 1970; pp 1-45 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Dialysis I (Summary of various peptides), 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 47)
    - untitled, pp 0-118 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - untitled, pp 119-220 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Dialysis II, 1970; pp 0-147 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Chromatograms - Sec, undated; pp 1-12 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Amino acid analyses 123,129-B chain chimp, undated; pp 1-46 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Amino acid analyses 2-101, 2-103, undated; pp 0-119 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Amino acid analyses - Edmans on Tp9, undated; 2-133-1, 2-136,2-137 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Amino acid analyses - chromatograms, undated; data work sheets 4-8 - 4-63. pp 1-97 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Amino acid analyses - chromatograms, undated; data work sheets 4-119-2 - 4-183-2. pp J-129 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Amino acid analyses - chromatograms, undated; data work sheets 4-216-1 - 4-237-2. pp 1-107 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Amino acid analyses - chromatograms, undated; data work sheets 4-242-1 - 4-290. pp 1-109 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Amino acid analyses - chromatograms, undated; data work sheets 5-70-1-1 - 5-125-2. pp 1-34 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Amino acid analyses, undated; data work sheets (photocopies) S-43 - S-149-2. pp 1-176 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Amino acid analyses, undated; data work sheets (photocopies) S-151-1 - S-243-1. pp 1-112 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Amino acid analyses, undated; data work sheets (photocopies) S-250 - S-340-1. pp 1-213 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Amino acid analyses, undated; data work sheets (photocopies) S-341 - S-410. pp 1-200 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Amino acid analyses, undated; data work sheets (photocopies) S-411 - S-456. pp 1-166 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Carboxy peptidase - Amino acid analyses, undated; data work sheets (photocopies) Cl-90 - Cl-431. pp 1-123 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Edman - Amino acid analyses, undated; data work sheets (photocopies) E-83 - 431, H-253, 301, 377. pp 1-210 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Graphs made from data work sheet information (photocopies), 6 folders (Box 51)
    - S-0 - S-246, undated; pp 0-87 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Cummings S-136 - 205, undated; pp 0-26 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Peptic hydrolysates - Roy S-249-294, undated; pp 0-47 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Chymotryptic - Roy S-296-345, undated; pp 0-63 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - S-346-422, undated; pp 1-78 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - S-423-462, undated; pp 1-48 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Laboratory techniques and equipment instructions collected by W. Hausmann (investigator in Craig lab), pp 1-92 (Box 51, Folder 7)
- Instruction manuals, 10 (Box 52)
  For care, maintenance and use of various pieces of equipment installed in Craig laboratory.
  Important for drawings of circuiting. Some of the manuals are marked for special attention, some have lists of various parts, and some have correspondence attached.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by name of manufacturer.
  - Beckman Instruments (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Brinkmann Instruments (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Buchler Instruments (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Coleman Instrument (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Gilford Instrument (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Ivan Sorval (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - Nuclear-Chicago, 2 folders (Box 52, Folder 7-8)
  - Oertling (Box 52, Folder 9)
  - Photovolt (Box 52, Folder 10)
  - Research Specialties (Box 52, Folder 11)
  - Varian aerograph (glass chromatograph) (Box 52, Folder 12)
- Accounting records, 1970-1973; 11
  - Accounting records, 1970 July-1973 June (Box 69)
  - Accounting records, Spectroscopic laboratory, 1972 July-1973 December (Box 70)
- Special formats, 12
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
  - 3x4 glass slides, 7 boxes; 3 4 glass slides (some duplicates) most bound in black tape, some in aluminum
    Selected from scientific illustrations for lectures.
    Arranged by negative numbers. Follows same arrangement as 5x7 negatives.
    - 3x4 glass slides, 92 items (Box 53)
      - #16,000's - 28,000's, undated
      - #30,000's - 36,000's, 1939-1951
    - 3x4 glass slides, 91 items (Box 54)
      - #37,000's, 1947
      - #1-900's, undated 1948 1952 1957
      - #1,000's, 1949-1950, undated
    - 3x4 glass slides, 1951-1954; 91 items (Box 55)
      Includes #2,000's - 5,000's - nd.
    - 3x4 glass slides, 1954-1958; 90 items (Box 56)
      Includes #5,000's cont'd - 7,000's -.
    - 3x4 glass slides, 90 items (Box 57)
      - #7,000's cont'd - 9,000's, 1958-1959
      - 1960
    - 3x4 glass slides, 1960-1962; 90 items (Box 58)
      Includes #60- 's cont'd - 62- 's-.
    - 3x4 glass slides, 67 items (Box 59)
      - 1962-1968
      - untitled
        17 unnumbered [nd] includes CCD apparatus.
  - 2x2 lantern slides (some duplicates), 2 boxes
    Bound in black tape or aluminum. Selected from scientific illustrations for lectures.
    Arranged by negative numbers. Follows same arrangement as 5x7 negatives and those not identified by negative numbers arranged in groupings of what appears to be lecture identification.
    - 2x2 lantern slides, 201 items (Box 60)
      Includes: 27,000's - 37,000's; 1 - 9,000's; 60- 's - 68- 's; and includes those not identified by negative numbers.
    - 2x2 lantern slides, 131 items (Box 61)
      Includes those not identified by negative numbers.
  - 5x7 negatives, 1935-1973
    Includes some duplicates. When available prints included with negatives. In some instances print only available. Includes several glass negatives (of crystals). From 1969-1973 only order is by date and so arranged. Some earlier negatives (by date) are filed with appropriate groups. Where available publication information cited. Undated negatives [nd] at end preceding negatives on apparatus. 5x7 negatives on apparatus. Some identified. Includes negatives of commercial equipment and many duplicate negatives. Negatives not numbered and undated [nd] at end of file.
    Arranged in numerical and approximate chronological order.
    - (ca. 600) 5x7 negatives, 1935-1957 (Box 62)
    - (ca. 600) 5x7 negatives, 1957-1970 (Box 63)
    - (ca. 350) 5x7 negatives; apparatus, 1971-1973, undated (Box 64)
  - Lab data, 23 folders (Box 65)
    Illustrations by graphics dept.; negatives and prints. Identified when possible. See individual folder for description.
    - Prints and drawings (Box 65, Folder 1)
      Identified by negative number. Includes negatives.
    - Absorbance at 280 M (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - Absorbance ninhydrin (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Acetic acid (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - Angiotensin, 1973 (Box 65, Folder 5)
      See Biochem 12 (1973) '4950-4957
    - Angiotensin, 1973 (Box 65, Folder 6)
      See Chimia 27 (1973) 381-382
    - Bacitracin (Box 65, Folder 7)
      Includes negatives.
    - Bacitracin-absorbance 252m (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Bacitracin - sephadex (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - Binding of N-acetyl-D-glusamide... (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - CCD curves, 1967 (Box 65, Folder 11)
      See Separation science 2 (1967) 487-499
    - HAc in water, ethanol 10%, 20%, 30% (Box 65, Folder 12)
    - Insulin A chain (Box 65, Folder 13)
    - Membrane thickness (Box 65, Folder 14)
    - Molecular weight (Box 65, Folder 15)
    - Polypeptides, 1972 (Box 65, Folder 16)
      Includes negative. See Progress in peptide research v. 2, 1972. (#256 in Craig bibliography).
    - Sodium taurocholate (Box 65, Folder 17)
    - Thin film dialysis of 3 decapeptides (Box 65, Folder 18)
    - Tyrocidines, 1965 (Box 65, Folder 19)
      See JACS 87: 18 (1965) 4196-4198
    - Transfers effluent (Box 65, Folder 20)
    - Tyr-gly-Tyr peptides (Box 65, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified (Box 65, Folder 22)
    - Apparatus. Some identified (Box 65, Folder 23)
      Includes 8x10 negatives.
  - Photographs and drawing of apparatus (Package 65a)
    Includes display photographs of CCD apparatus.
  - Reels of film, 1961
    Conditions Governing Access
    RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media, due to the specialized equipment necessary to facilitate playback. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
    Reels 7, 8, and 9 include a demonstration of the counter-current apparatus used in the 1961 Rockefeller Institute Christmas Lecture series, "Separating Things", given by Professors Lyman Craig, Stanford Moore, and William Stein. [Editor's note: Original reels - make copies if to be used].
    - Reel #1 - Craig - CCDA (Box 66)
      RAC is unable to provide access to the original item, due to the specialized equipment necessary to facilitate playback. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
    - Reel #2 - Dr. Craig. Cells. Color (Box 66)
    - Reel #3 - Unidentified (Box 66)
    - Reel #4 - Unidentified (Box 66)
    - Reel #5 - Unidentified (Box 66)
    - Reel #6 - RI - Dr. Craig lecture (Box 66)
    - Reel #7 - Dr. Craig - "Countercurrent" -RU Christmas lectures (color and sound). video only, original, 4 " on core, 16 mm (Box 66)
    - Reel #8 - Dr. Stein - RU Christmas lectures. sound only, original, 4 " on core, 16 mm (Box 66)
    - 12" reel of film - black and white with sound finished film from NBC (presents: Continental Classroom) ca. 1/2 hour. Some bio details - countercurrent (Can be used), 1 item (Box 67)
    - Film Reel #9 (RC-12), 1981 September (Box 68)
      Film reel #9 [RC-12]. Countercurrent apparatus demonstration, (1) 7" reel. synchronized color and sound, 7" reel.
      Acquisition from Graphic Services.
      Also includes video only of 1) automated 1000-tube apparatus in laboratory, 2) 25-tube "sample-in-middle" apparatus [information from Dr. Stanford Moore, September 1981].
- Collected reprints, 4 volumes